其次，我们看到所有的文章都涉及到
Secondly, we saw which all articles were involved.
第三，从历史的角度审视《浦那公约》
Thirdly we saw the history angle of the Poona Pact.
如果有任何困惑或问题，你可以现在就问我
If there is any confusion or difficulty you can ask me right now.
英迪拉 · 索尼，最高法院判决... ... 有什么混淆吗？
Indira Sawhney, Supreme Court judgment...is there any confusion?
萨克西高尔，这是另一个话题
Sakshi Gaur, that is another topic.
选举债券的话题将在稍后讨论
The electoral bond topic will be discussed later.
下节课的下一个主题
Next topic in the next class.
下一批非学院课程开始了，每个星期三开始分批
The next batch of Unacademy is starting. Every Wednesday the batches start.
这项课程是为双语考生准备的
The mission is for bilinguals.
Lakshya 是为印地语考生准备的
Lakshya is for Hindi
另外"探索"是给英语考生准备的
And Expedition for English students.
把这个告诉你的朋友们
Tell your friends about this.
你知道你得到了一个结构化的课程表
You are aware that you get a structural curriculum.
完全的准备，不管是预考还是正考
Complete preparation. Whether it is of prelims or mains.
下课后你可以下载笔记
After the class you can download the notes.
好的，下节课我们会消除所有的疑问
Okay. In the next class we will clear all the doubts.
你可以在评论区留下任何问题
You can leave any question in the comment section.
我会回答的
I will answer it.
我们明天上午见
We shall meet tomorrow morning.
努力学习，少做娱乐
Study hard and do less enjoyment.
下课
Okay. Jai Hind.
加姜了吗？
Did you put ginger?
你怎么情绪转变这么快？
How can you switch so easily?
刚才你在教学生的时候还在微笑
A moment back you were smiling while teaching students.
你出来的那一刻就很伤心
And you are sad the moment you came out.
发生了什么？
What happened?
你在想昨晚的事吗？
Are you thinking about last night?
算了吧，兄弟
Forget it, buddy.
我怎么能不想呢，兄弟？
How can I leave it, buddy?
我没想到他会这样
I did not expect this from him.
你不该对他有所期望
You had expectations from the wrong person.
我知道他不会来
I knew that he wouldn't come.
人们在成为公务员之后会发生变化
People change after becoming IAS.
他也变了
He has also changed.
不要为此难过
Don't be sad about it.
我很高兴他不来了
I am happy that he is not coming.
我的信仰受到了伤害，兄弟
My faith has been hurt, buddy.
我总是说他是我们的朋友
I always used to say that he is our friend.
他竟然直接退群了，多么幼稚的行为？
He left the WhatsApp group. What childish behavior?
我原以为他会来参加你们的婚礼
I had thought that if he would come to attend your marriage
然后请他去学院上课
then would ask him to take a lecture in the institute.
如果老师的朋友是一个公务员，并且能做一次演讲，那一定会产生很大影响
If the teacher's friend is an IAS and gives a lecture then it has an impact.
这是一种激励
It is motivational.
什么？
What?
你以我的婚姻为借口，邀请阿比拉什
You are inviting Abhilash for a lecture in your coaching center
到你的课堂做演讲
under the pretext of my marriage.
不，兄弟，你的婚姻才是最重要的
No, buddy. Your marriage was the priority.
- 演讲稍后再说-别说了兄弟
- Lecture can be held later. - Leave it, buddy.
你根本不担心他会不会参加我的婚礼
You are not worried about the fact that he is not attending my wedding.
你在担心他不能做那愚蠢的演讲
You are worried about the fact that he cannot give his stupid lecture
在你那没用的学院里
in your useless institute.
不，兄弟，你在说什么？
No, buddy. What are you saying?
你真是个两面派，兄弟，你到底有没有正直的一面？
You are a two-faced, buddy. Do you have integrity in you or not?
好在你没有考上公务员
Good that you did not become an IAS.
你要是考上了，那么你一定是个贪腐的公务员
If you would have become then you would be a dishonest and bribe-taker IAS
你知道自己在说什么吗？
Do you have an idea of what you are saying?
与其为你的朋友感到高兴，不如奉承一下这位收藏家
Rather than being happy for your friend you want to flatter the collector.
自己去请他吧，但不要把我牵扯进来
Do that but do not involve me.
如果是这样的话，你为什么没考上公务员呢？
If that was the case why couldn't you become IAS?
你应该考一个，去世界各地做演讲
You should have become one and go around the world to give the lecture.
你通过了 UPSC 吗？
Did you crack UPSC?
你也来过这里，你考上公务员了吗？
You had also come here. Did you become an IAS?
但是我在别的地方成功了，你在做什么？
But I became successful somewhere else. What are you doing?
这么多年来，你一直在这个地方
You are here for the last so many years at Old Rajinder Nagar.
除此之外你什么也做不了，所以成为了一名教师
You could not do anything else so became a teacher.
记住，你一直都是个失败者
Remember that you have always been a loser.
至少喝杯茶吧，我都下楼去买姜了
At least drink tea. I had gone down to get ginger.
这是一次政治集会
This is a political rally.
让牧师和他的志愿者为集会安排卡车
Let minister and his volunteers make arrangements for trucks for a rally.
这不是我们的工作
This is not our job.
好的，先生
Okay, sir.
我们的责任是保证集会期间的安全，这是我们的工作
Our responsibility is of security during the rally and that we will do.
- 好的，先生-现在就去
- Okay sir. - Go, now.
你昨晚的行为很无礼，每一份友谊都值得第二次机会
我们曾经的关系就像三脚架一样，你还记得吗
很好
Yes.
又有新面孔了，好极了
Nice and new faces. Great.
早上好，你们好吗？
Good morning. How are you all?
是的，先生
Yes, sir.
看到你们让我想起了我在备考 UPSC 的日子
Seeing you all I remember my days of preparation for UPSC.
那是2002年
In 2002. Right.
整个国家动荡不安
Riots were going on in the entire country
我们在打艾阿斯战役
and we were fighting the battle of IAS.
就在那儿
Exactly there.
我过去常常坐在你坐的地方，进行我的第一次预考
I used to sit where you are sitting and gave my first prelim.
你知道发生了什么吗? 我没通过
Do you know what happened? I did not clear it.
我考了第二次，但仍然没通过
I gave the second time but still did not clear.
直到第三次，我通过了预考
I gave the third time and I cleared prelims
但没有通过正考
but did not clear in the mains.
直到第四次尝试，我才放弃了
I had given up hope till the fourth attempt.
我以为我做不到，所以就放弃了
I had thought that I cannot do it so give up.
我开始感到羞愧
I started feeling ashamed.
因为我的朋友找到了一份100万卢比的工资
Because my mates were being hired for 10 lakhs.
而我却还在花我父母的钱考试
And I was still giving exams on my parents' money.
情况变得如此糟糕，以至于你需要向朋友借钱
The condition becomes so worse that you need to borrow money from your friends.
但是什么时候呢？
But till when?
直到什么时候你才会向你的朋友要钱？
Till when will you ask money from your friends?
因为有一天当他们拒绝的时候，他们会很伤心
Because one day when they refuse it hurts.
- 你感觉不好吗?-是的，先生
- Do you feel bad? - Yes, sir.
我晚上睡不着
I could not sleep at night.
即使是你也不能睡觉
Even you must not be able to sleep.
这是 UPSC
This is UPSC.
你不能轻易通过考试
You cannot clear it easily.
不要高估自己
Don't overestimate
认为既然你来到这里，参加教练培训
that now that you have come here and attending coaching
你就可以很容易地通过考试
you will be able to clear it easily.
不可能的
No.
那样我们都能成为公务员了
We had also come to become IAS.
结局会怎样？
What happened?
我们失败了
We did not clear.
然后感觉自己变老了
Then I felt that I am getting older.
应该怎么做？
What should be done?
继续前进，开始教学
Moved ahead and started teaching.
一定有很多学生
There must be many students
他们一定是从工程，银行或者其他工作中辞职来到这里的？
who must have come here leaving their engineering, banking, or any other job?
是不是？
Have you left?
是的，先生
Yes, sir.
谁让你这样做的? 谁给你的勇气？
Who had asked you to do so? Who asked you to be so daring?
你放弃了你的好工作来到这里
You left your good job and came here.
没有必要成为一名公务员
It is not necessary that you will become an IAS.
你不应该辞掉这份工作，你知道为什么吗？
You shouldn't have left the job. Do you know why?
因为花了很长时间，我才意识到你很难找到一份好工作
Because very late I realized that you get a job with great difficulty.
而辞职却很容易
And we leave it easily.
别管了，我们能做什么？
Leave it. What can we do?
让我们从经济大萧条开始今天的课程
Let's start today's session with the Great Economic Depression.
好吗？
Okay?
你会因为这样一件小事而放弃教学课程吗？
Will you leave coaching for such a small matter?
这是一件小事吗？
Is it a small thing?
教师是在生活中取得成就并激励他人的人
A teacher is one who has achieved something in life and inspires others.
在 UPSC，有些老师失败了
And here in UPSC, there are those teachers who have failed.
不会有公务员会亲自来教你
No IAS will come to teach you himself.
如果他考上了，那么他为什么要教书？
If he is an IAS then why will he teach?
公务员是人民公仆，而不是为社会服务的人
IAS is a public servant and not the one who serves society.
但至少他应该通过一次正考
But at least he should have cleared mains once.
就连我都通过了两次预备考试
Even I have cleared prelims twice.
这就是为什么他只是在教 GS
That is why he is just teaching GS.
他最擅长这个了
He is best at that.
有些人擅长教学，有些人擅长学习
Some are good at teaching and some are good at their studies.
我们的老师擅长教学，让我们先学习几天，然后再做决定
Our teacher is good at teaching. Let's study for few days and then decide.
这是我最后一次机会了
This is my last attempt.
我的 GS 已经很弱了
My GS is already weak.
改革之后，分数从600增加到1000
After a change in pattern, it has increased from 600 marks to 1000 marks.
我怎么能向一个放弃了第四次机会的老师学习呢？
How can I study from a teacher who had given up on the fourth attempt?
他是一个失败者，这是不能改变的
It cannot change that he is a failure.
你必须自学
You have to study on your own.
培训只是一种指导
Coaching is just for guidance.
没错，我就是这个意思
Exactly. That is what I am saying.
那个失败者怎么能引导别人呢？
How will that person guide correctly who himself has failed?
你告诉我
You tell me.
那个人将如何帮助你到达你的目的地
How will that person help you to reach your destination
谁不知道德里的道路？
who does not know the roads of Delhi?
- 如果有人叫你去你会去吗?-听着..
- Will you go if anyone asks you to go? - Listen...
许多人认为普拉卡什先生是他们的导师
Many people consider Prakash sir as their Guru.
我要离开教练岗位了
I am leaving coaching.
算了吧，你的费用不会退还的
Leave it. Your fees will not be refunded.
这怎么可能? 他们必须退还费用
How is that possible? They will have to refund the fees.
去试试吧
Go and give it a try.
你来这里是要通过 UPSC 还是要退款的？
Have you come here to do UPSC or try to get fees back?
- 走，走...-他们不会退钱的
- Go, go... - They will not refund the fees.
不，不... 没有退费的程序
No, no...there is no procedure for the refund of fees.
你没看合同吗？
Didn't you read the prospectus?
求你了先生，我需要拿回来
Please, sir. I will need it back.
你报名参加其他培训机构了吗？
Are you joining any other coaching?
不，先生我要回家，在家里学习
No, sir. I am going home and will study there.
靠近点
Come close.
Come closer.
先生
Sir.
没有指导，你不可能通过UPSC
Without coaching you will not be able to clear UPSC.
我知道，但我母亲病得很重
I know that but my mother is seriously ill.
发生了什么？
What happened?
她有老年痴呆症
She has Alzheimer's.
- 忘东西?-是的，先生
- Forgetting things? - Yes sir.
每个人都有这个问题
Everyone has this problem.
即使是我自己也深受其害，我往往会忘记很多事情
Even I am suffering from this. I tend to forget many things.
去看医生
Get yourself checked by a doctor.
不，科学家说那些忘记的人是非常聪明的
No, no. Scientists say that those who forget are very intelligent.
先生，根据那些科学家的说法
Sir according to those scientists
这是世界上第七危险的疾病
this is the 7th most dangerous disease of the world.
这是一种非常危险的疾病
It is a very dangerous disease.
我母亲的病情很严重，她快把我忘了
My mother's case is very severe. She is forgetting me.
她去买菜，却赶上一辆公共汽车去叔叔家
She goes to buy vegetables but catches a bus to goes to uncle's house.
有很多问题，先生
There is a lot of problems, sir.
你为什么让你妈妈去买蔬菜？
Why do you send your mother to buy vegetables?
这就是为什么先生，我必须回家，这样我才能去买蔬菜
That is why sir I will have to go so that I can go and buy vegetables.
她需要我，先生，求你了
She needs me, sir. Please.
规则就是规则，学院不退还费用
Rules are rules. Institute does not refund fees.
先生，在特殊情况下，有关费用可在扣除15% 后退还
Sir, in exceptional cases the fees can be refunded after a deduction of 15%
招生简章里面有写的
This is also written in the prospectus.
还写着应该在14天之内
It is also written that it should be within 14 days.
你也应该读读这个
You should have read that also.
今天是我的第一天，先生，今天是我的第一天
This is my first day. Today is my first day, sir.
哦，不
Oh no.
那你这样，写一个情况说明
Do one thing. Write an application
让经理签字，并附上医疗文件证明
get it signed by the manager and attach the medical papers.
先生，我必须从家里拿到文件，这需要时间
Sir, I will have to get the papers from home and that will take time.
必须附上证明文件
You will have to attach papers for proof.
先生，为什么一个人要对他的母亲撒谎
Sir, why would one lie about his mother.
是的，先生
Yes, sir.
你是谁？
Who are you?
达莉娅
Dhairya.
先生，求你了
Sir, please try.
你要保持耐心，打电话要文件
You keep patience and call for papers.
再见
Bye.
去吧
Go, now.
把文件拿来，这很容易办到
Get the papers. It will be done easily.
好吧
Okay.
好的，谢谢，先生
Okay, thank you, sir.
你以为他们会退费
You had thought that they would return the fees.
有没有其他方法可以退还费用？
Is there any other way out by which fees can be refunded?
你疯了吗? 如果你再找借口的话，你会被抓住的
Are you crazy? You will be caught if you go with another excuse.
找条路离开这里
Find out a way out from here.
我该怎么办？
What do I do?
伪造证明
Make fake papers.
他没有说她得了水痘，只是说她得了老年痴呆症
He did not say that she had chicken pox but said that she has Alzheimer's.
我从哪里可以弄到假证明？
From where can I get fake papers made?
在 Patel Nagar 有一个男孩
There is a boy in Patel Nagar.
他是一名医生，在民用医院执业
He is a doctor and was practicing in Civil Hospital.
离开诊所后，他现在正在为 UPSC 做准备
He is now preparing for UPSC after leaving his practice.
- 他能做点什么-你认识他吗？
- He can do something. - Do you know him?
- 为什么我会认识他?-哦，不..
- Why will I know him? - Oh no...
但我看见他和桑迪普兄弟在地铁里
But I saw him with brother Sandeep in the metro.
桑迪普兄弟不行，他太理想主义了
Brother Sandeep, will not do. He is too idealistic.
你不能因为害怕困难而继续生活下去
You cannot move on in life fearing difficulties
努力的人不会失败
and those who try do not fail.
什么？
What?
这是伟大诗人索汉 · 拉尔 · 德维维迪的一首诗
This is a poem of great poet Sohan Lal Dwivedi.
至少尝试一下
At least give it a try.
我会找他谈的，但是这很困难
I will talk to you but it is very difficult.
他的想法很消极
He thinks so negatively.
是的
Yes, he is.
阿比拉什，当你感到消极，认为什么都没有发生在生活中
Abhilash, when you feel negative and think nothing is happening in life
那么昆瓦尔·纳拉扬的诗《安提姆·翁查伊》
then poem 'Antim Oonchayi' by Kunwar Narayan
会在困难时期给你希望
shows hope in times of distress.
嘿，看看这个
Hey, read this.
这是我给你的礼物，你会永远记得我的
It is a gift from me. You will remember me always for this.
仅仅学习教学大纲是不够的
Studying the syllabus is not enough.
你还要读这些诗歌来激励自己
You have to read all this to motivate yourself.
这三句改变了像我这样的人
These three lines have changed people like me.
注意这三句，兄弟
Pay attention to these three lines, brother.
- 格里，听着-我在听
- Guri, listen. - I am listening.
“天上不可能有洞”
'There cannot be a hole in the sky.'
- 一块石头...-别说了，别教训我
- A stone... - Stop it and don't give a lecture.
你要是能把背诗的功力用在教学大纲上
If instead of this you would have studied your syllabus
那你就可以通过一次正考了
then you could have cleared mains once.
你为什么现在说到正考？
Why are you talking about the mains now?
这声音太大了，把它调成震动模式
This is so loud, Guri. Keep it on vibrate mode.
振动会让我很痒
Vibration causes tickling.
这就是为什么我必须把音量调到最大
That is why I have to keep it at full volume.
如果我错过了她的电话，普拉加蒂会责骂我
Pragati scold me if i miss her call.
你好
Hello.
你好..
Hello...
格里
Guri.
阿比拉什
Abhilash.
怎么回事，兄弟？
What is this, buddy?
你愿意这样邀请我参加你的婚礼吗？
Will you invite me for your marriage in this way?
通过短信？
Over text?
有些朋友是特别的
Some friends are special.
那个特别的朋友离开了群组
And those special friends leave the group.
这是我的工作号码
That is my official number.
婚礼在哪里举行？
Where is the marriage taking place?
在卡纳尔
In Karnal.
当然，这是一场盛大的婚礼，所以一定要排场隆重
Of course, it is a marriage of a jatt so must be with great pomp and show.
当然
Of course.
在我们的团体中，必须举行盛大的表演，这样客人才能尽情享受
In our society pomp and show has to happen so that guests can enjoy.
我一定会来的
I will surely come.
看看这个，兄弟
Check it out, buddy.
你一定没有时间
You must not be having time.
现在公务员先生不会参加每个人的婚礼
Now Mr. Collector will not attend everyone's marriage.
但一定会参加你的婚礼
But will surely attend your wedding.
格里，你还在生我的气吗？
Guri, are you still angry with me?
没有
No.
让我们忘记一切
Let's forget everything.
已经很久了
It's been a long time.
我会忘记的
I would have forgotten
如果你在过去的六年里给我打过一次电话
If you would have called me once in the last six years.
我很晚才意识到
I realized it very late.
下周我要去安巴拉
Next week I am coming to Ambala.
会来卡纳尔见你
Will come to Karnal to meet you.
我不在卡纳尔
I am not in Karnal.
我是来德里工作的，需要一些时间... ..
I had come to Delhi for some work. It will take some time...
你在德里吗？
Are you in Delhi?
是的
Yes.
那我们今天见面吧
Then let's meet today.
我也在德里，我也是为了一些公务而来
Even I am in Delhi. I had come for some official work.
就这么定了，我们今天晚上见个面
It is final that we are meeting today evening.
让 SK 也和你一起
Get SK also along with you.
好吧
Okay.
喂... ？
Hello...?
好吧，我会转告SK的
Okay fine. I will talk to SK
好的，那就把你的位置发给我，不见不散
Okay then text me where you are. I will come.
这是怎么回事？
What is this?
你梦想成为一名公务员，而且已经从腐败开始了
You dream of becoming a civil servant and started with corruption already.
这一定是你的主意
This must be your idea.
不，这不是我的主意，是他的主意
No, it was not mine but his idea.
- 听着，巴克蒂...-普拉加蒂
- Look, Bhakti... - Pragati.
对不起... 普拉加蒂，听着，我只是想要回我的学费
Sorry...Pragati, look I am just taking my fees back.
相信我，因为这没有威胁
Trust me because of this there is no threat
你们公务员的道德和诚信
to your ethics and integrity of civil services.
好吧，如果你对你的工作不认真，我该告诉你什么？
Fine. What should I tell you if you are not serious about your job?
什么? 我不是认真的! 我？
What? I am not serious! I?
拿着这个
Hold this.
我的一天从印度报开始
My day starts with Hindu (newspaper)
最后以古鲁格舍德拉(杂志)结束
and ends with Yojna and Kurukshetra (magazines).
我开始觉得 Laxmikant 是我特别的朋友
I have started feeling that Laxmikant is my special friend.
GC Leong和比品钱德拉是我的叔叔
GC Leong and Bipin Chandra are my uncles.
波谱和经济调查像远亲一样嘲弄我
Spectrum and Economic Survey taunt me like distant relatives.
这是 UPSC，没那么简单
It is UPSC. It is not that easy.
为了节省时间，我每天都吃同样的食物
I eat the same food every day to save time.
即使这样，教学大纲也不会过时
Even then the syllabus does not get over.
我不在家看电影和板球
I am away from watching movies and cricket.
由于做笔记，我的拇指指纹已经变了
The fingerprint of my thumb has changed due to making notes.
我梦见第三次世界大战
I dream of the third world war.
中国轰炸了印度
China has bombed India.
还有很多其他的紧张关系
There are so many other tensions.
即便如此，我仍然保持着“永不言败”的态度
Even then I always keep my 'Never-say-die' attitude up.
你现在说我不是认真的..
And you are saying that I am not serious...
这与努力学习无关
It is not about hard work sir.
这是一个高原则的工作，但你永远不会明白这一点
It is a high principled job but you will never understand this.
嘿，你们两个已经开始吵架了
Hey, you both have started fighting.
冷静，放松，一定有什么误会
Chill. Relax. There must be some misunderstanding.
每个人都知道所有的研究都是认真的，不是吗？
Everyone knows that all are serious about studies. Isn't it?
来吧，握握手
Come on shake hands.
握握手，冷静一下
Shake hands and chill.
- 握手...-你疯了吗？
- Shake hands... - Are you mad?
你来吧，兄弟
You do it, buddy.
- 拜托...-不
- Come on... - No.
没问题，和我握手吧
No problem, shake hands with me.
我们去参加研讨会吧
Let's go to attend the seminar.
他们是什么样的人？
What kind of people are they?
我们去参加研讨会吧，我们要迟到了
Let's go and attend the seminar. We are getting late.
不，我要去见桑迪普兄弟，拿文件
No, I have to meet brother Sandeep, to get documents.
一位公务员来做演讲
An IAS officer is coming.
那又怎么样? 我一会儿再看录像
So what? I will watch the video later.
这是现场直播
This is live.
你不看电视上的板球比赛吗? 你去过体育场吗？
Don't you watch cricket on TV? Have you ever gone to a stadium?
板球与 IAS 有什么联系吗？
Does cricket have any combination with IAS?
我发誓，跟你讲道理是没用的
I swear, it is useless talking to you.
好吧，你也走吧
Okay, you too leave.
普拉卡什先生？
Prakash sir?
是的
Yes.
再考虑一下
Just give it a second thought.
从他那里再学习几天，然后再做决定
Study for some more days from him and then decide.
不，桑迪普兄弟，预考就快开始了，我没有时间做实验
No, brother Sandeep, Prelims is very close and I don't have time to experiment.
请试着和他谈谈
Please try to talk to him.
好吧，我会和雷迪谈谈
Okay, I will talk to Reddy.
也许你就能拿到证明了
Maybe your work will be done.
真的吗? 谢谢
Really? Thank you.
我这样做是因为我知道金钱的价值
I am doing this because I understand the value of money.
但是这种事不能一次又一次地发生
This will not happen again and again.
不，不会的
No, not at all.
今天有一个研讨会，一个政府的官员应该会来演讲
There was a seminar today. An IAS officer was supposed to come.
是的，正在演讲
Yes, that is going on.
你没去吗？
Didn't you go?
我想见见你
I wanted to meet you.
去那里会发生什么？
What is going to happen by going there?
重要的是自学
Self-study is what matters.
你应该去的
You should have gone.
听听他们的专业经验是很好的
It is good to listen to their professional experience.
这对面试很有帮助
It helps during the interview.
把这个放下吧，走吧
Leave this and go.
我得洗衣服
I had to wash my clothes.
学院会录像，所以我稍后会看录像
The institute does recording so I will watch the video later.
你在体育场看过板球比赛吗？
Have you watched a cricket match in the stadium?
它更令人兴奋
It is more enjoyable.
修好了，走吧
This is working. Now go.
先生，官员不是来你们学院的吗？
Sir, don't IAS officers come to your institute?
不，我今年不做培训
No. I am not doing coaching this year.
什么? 你不去吗？
What? Don't you go for coaching?
不，我今年要休息一下
No. I am taking a break this year.
为什么？
Why?
我以后再告诉你，说来话长，你现在就去吧
I will tell you later. It is a long story. You go now.
去吧，你是来这洗衣服的吗？
Go. Have you come to Rajendra Nagar to wash clothes?
好吧，我这就去
Okay, I will go.
你好吗，桑迪普？
How are you, Sandeep?
你好，瓦利亚先生？
How are you, Mr. Walia?
管灯坏了吗？
Is the tube light not working?
是的，坏掉了，阿比拉什修好了它
Yes, it was not working properly. Abhilash repaired it.
他是个有才华的孩子，如果搅拌机坏了，他也能修理
He is a talented boy. He can repair mixer as well if it is not working.
如果有什么问题一定要告诉我
Do let me know if there is any problem.
这些琐碎的问题不应该干扰你的学习
Such petty problems should not disturb your studies.
这一次，你一定能通过考试
This time you surely have to clear IAS.
叔叔，我房间里的电视声音..
Uncle, the TV sound in my room...
桑迪普，当你成为公务员的时候别忘了我
Sandeep, don't forget me when you become IAS.
你在我家住了这么久
You have stayed in my house for so long.
-不会的-别忘了给我甜点
- Not at all. - Don't forget to give me sweetmeat.
- 叔叔，那个电视音量...-多向他学习
- Uncle, that TV volume... - Learn something from him.
有问题吗？
Problem?
他没有关电视，而是告诉我... ..
He does not switch off his TV and is telling me...
- 快走-好的
- Go now. - Okay.
我们很荣幸能邀请到政府官员，我们的校友
We are proud to have the Pratham IAS alumni
阿努拉达·蒂瓦里女士，加瓦尔驻北阿坎德邦的IAS委员
Miss Anuradha Tiwari, IAS commissioner Garwal, Uttrakhand is amongst us.
请以雷鸣般的掌声欢迎她
Please welcome her with thundering round of applause.
作为加瓦尔驻北阿坎德邦的委员
As commissioner of Garwal, Uttrakhand
这是我维护法律和秩序的责任
this is my responsibility to maintain law and order.
公务员的生活中有许多情感上的挑战
There are many emotional challenges in the life of a civil servant.
但是没有混乱
But there is no confusion.
谢谢你在费用问题上帮我
- Thank you for helping me with the fees matter.
宪法为你指明了道路
The constitution shows you the way.
夫人，政客们干涉了多少？
Madam, how much do the politicians interfere?
你妈妈知道她得了老年痴呆症吗？
Does your mother know that she has Alzheimer's?
他们做他们的工作，你做你的
They do their job and you do yours.
但是两者有着相同的目标
But both have the same goal.
夫人，我们怎样才能保持动力直到最后一次尝试？
Madam, how can we keep ourselves motivated till the last attempt?
这是一个很好的问题
This is a very good question.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我也不得不做了很多尝试才通过考试
I too had to give many attempts before I cleared.
你知道恐惧和挫折
You know fear and frustrations
都是这次旅程的乘客
are the fellow passengers of this journey.
他们会一直在那里
And they will always be there.
把注意力集中在你的旅程上
Keep the focus on your journey.
没有必要和其他乘客交谈
There is no need to talk to your fellow passengers.
但是夫人经过这么多次失败的尝试后，你不觉得压力太大了吗？
But madam after so many failed attempts didn't you feel the pressure too much?
现在我应该放弃了
Now I should give up.
这个问题非常贴近我的心
This question is very close to my heart.
如果你是个女孩
When you are a girl
属于一个东正教家庭
who belongs to an orthodox family
你22岁就结婚了
where you are married at the age of 22...
你属于印度一个非常落后的地区
you belong to a very backward area of India.
你连英语都不懂
You do not even know English.
因为你姐姐的固执，你只是在外面学习
You are just studying outside the house because of the stubbornness of your sister.
最重要的是，你每次尝试都失败了
And on top of that you fail in every attempt.
过去的每一天我都觉得要放弃
Every day I used to feel to give up.
也许我能做到
Maybe I could have done it.
事实上，我肯定会这么做的
Actually, I would have definitely done it.
但就在那一刻，有人告诉了我一件非常好的事情
But at that moment someone told me a very good thing.
因此我的态度发生了180度的大转变
With that my attitude flipped 180 degrees.
你想听听是什么事吗？
Would you like to listen to that thing?
是的，夫人
Yes, madam.
听听这个故事
Listen to this story.
1981年，美国有一位教陶艺的教授
In 1981, there was a professor in US who used to teach Ceramics.
他做了一个实验
He did an experiment.
他把班级分成两组，给他们10天的时间
He divided his class into two groups and gave them 10 days of time.
对于第一组，他给出的任务是只做一个完美的罐子
To the first group, he gave a task of making just one perfect pot.
只做一个
Only one.
还有另一组
And to the other group
他要求同学们做尽可能多的陶罐
he asked to make as many pots as possible
而不用担心质量
without worrying about the quality.
两个小组都开始了他们的工作
Both the groups started their work.
10天后，教授看到了结果，大吃一惊
After seeing the results after 10 days the professor got surprised.
第二组不仅制作了比第一组更多的陶罐
The second group not only made more pots than the first group
而且每一个罐子都更好看，几乎完美
but every pot was better looking and almost perfect.
每个人都在想这是怎么发生的？
Everyone was thinking that how did this happen?
你知道这是怎么发生的吗？
Do you know how did this happen?
第一组被困在如何制作一个完美的罐子这个问题上
The first group was stuck on the point that how to make one perfect pot?
他们把所有的时间都花在了完美上
They spent the entire time in perfection.
但是另一组人尝试了，做出了糟糕的罐子
But the other group tried and made bad pots.
他们对它进行了改进，尝试并重新制作了这些罐子
They improved on it. Tried and made the pots again.
他们失败了，但是进步了
They failed but improved.
通过这种方式，他们从错误中吸取教训，制作出了漂亮的陶罐
And in this way learning from their mistakes they made beautiful pots.
所以这就是为什么不要害怕犯错
So that is why do not be scared of your mistakes.
不要逃避你的错误
Don't run away from your mistakes.
从你的错误和失败中学习，然后继续前进
Learn from your mistakes, failures, and move ahead.
告诉我这个故事的人现在在这里，这是一个巧合
It is a coincidence that the person who told me the story is present here.
当你第一次见到他
When you will meet him for the first time
你会觉得生活是没有希望的
you will feel that life is hopeless.
但是普拉卡什先生，这对我很有用
But Prakash sir it worked for me.
你很幸运，亲爱的
You are lucky, dear.
如果我读过这个实验
If I had read this experiment of the pot
那么即使是我也会第四次尝试
then even I would have given my fourth attempt.
我会站在讲台上而不是你
And I would be standing at the podium instead of you.
不过没关系，先生
But it is okay sir.
失败者只知道在哪里不能犯错误
The one who fails can only tell where not to make mistakes.
有时候最差的球员会成为全国最好的教练
Sometimes the worst player becomes the best coach in the country.
为什么？
Why?
你可以说是一个中等水平的球员
You could have said an average player.
所以坚强点，坚持住
So just be strong and stay there.
不要逃避失败
Don't run away from failures.
因为失败教会了你如何成为公务员
Because failure teaches you and makes you IAS.
你们一定都在读诗来获得动力
You all must be reading poems to get motivated.
我想和大家分享我最喜欢的一句诗
I want to share the favorite line of my favorite poem.
“谁说天上不会有洞... ...”
"Who says that a hole cannot be made in the sky..."
“带着信念扔一块石头... ...”
"Just throw one stone with faith..."
对
Right.
有了这个，我祝大家好运，不要放弃
With this, I would wish you luck and don't give up.
谢谢你
Thank you.
- 是不是很棒 SK?-是的
- Wasn't it good, SK? - Yes.
倾听是件好事
It was good to listen.
- 很好-演讲..
- Very good. - The speech was...
嘿，兄弟，看看周围
Hey, buddy. Just look around.
- 你在里面吗?-你在这里干什么？
- Were you inside? - What are you doing here?
我刚来，结束了吗？
I just came. Is it over?
你错过了
You missed it.
非常棒的演讲
It was very good.
很棒吗？
- Was it very good?
但你迟到了
But you were late.
你应该参加的
You should have attended it.
孩子，我和经理谈过了
Son, I spoke to the manager.
你只需要递交申请表就可以了，不需要医生证明
You just give the application and medical papers are not required.
这样就可以退款了
Your fees will be refunded.
没有人会对自己的母亲撒谎，不是吗？
No one would lie about his mother. Isn't it?
哪些费用，先生? 哪些费用？
Which fees, sir? Which fees?
你早上来的时候说你妈妈得了老年痴呆症
You had come in the morning saying that your mother has Alzheimer's
所以你想离开培训回家去吗
so you wish to leave coaching and go home.
我？
- Me?
不，不... 为什么我要离开这里？
No, no... Why will I leave the coaching?
我妈妈很好，我刚和她通过话
Mother is absolutely fine. I just spoke to her.
她刚才还在责骂我
She was scolding me.
很奇怪
Very strange.
你要求见我，所以我和经理谈了
You requested me hence I spoke to the manager.
否则，我为什么要这么做？
Otherwise, why would I?
先生，我不记得有这种事
Sir, I don't remember anything of this sort.
这一定是个梦
It must be a dream.
你全家都得了老年痴呆症
Your entire family has Alzheimer's.
看病去吧
Get yourself treated.
你想错了，我们没有..
You are thinking something wrong. We do not...
你就快拿回你的学费了，这是闹哪样？
Listen, you had gone to get your fees back so what happened now?
- 我不要退款-为什么？
- I don't want the refund. - Why?
- 你不打算离开了吗?-不，我不会离开的
- Are you not leaving coaching? - No, I am not leaving.
- 你为什么撒谎?-离开你们我还能去哪里？
- Why are you lying? - Where will I go leaving you all?
我们将一起成为公务员
Together we will become IAS.
- 好吧-你不记得他们以前怎么说的了吗？
- Okay. - Don't you remember what did they use to say?
什么？
What?
我们就像..
We are like a...
三脚架
Tripod.
他又做错事了
He is again doing something wrong.
我要留下来继续学习，你要我留下来
I am staying back for coaching. You were requesting me to stay back.
集中精力学习
Concentrate on your studies.
- 你有事瞒着我们-不..
- There is something you are not telling us. - No...
[模糊的谈话声]
[indistinct chatter]
“通过这种方式，收藏家经过的道路就像阿克巴已经通过”
"In this way, the collector passes by the road just like Akbar has passed."
“每个人的眼睛都盯着她的车，就像磁铁粘在铁上一样”
"Everyone's eyes are stuck on her car just like a magnet sticks to iron."
太好了
Great.
蓝色的灯塔..
Blue beacon...
那个蓝色的灯塔..
That blue beacon...
SK 先生自己就是一个失败者，那么他会教给我们什么呢
SK sir is a failure himself then what will he teach us.
学院聘请了什么样的教师？
What kind of teachers has the institute hired?
先生，我获得了非学院奖学金
Sir, I have got an Unacademy Combat scholarship.
很好，恭喜你
Great, congratulations.
上次我没有认真准备，所以我得了第六名
Last time I was not serious so I had the sixth rank.
现在我进了前三名，赢得了奖学金，先生
Now by coming in top three I have won a scholarship, sir.
很好
Very good.
感谢您和非学院
Thanks to you sir and Unacademy.
是你指引了我
You had guided me.
非学院的讲座和你的讲座帮助我拿到了奖学金
Lectures of Unacademy and your lectures helped me to get it.
所以这篇全文的修订和你们的准备工作将会非常棒
So this full-length revision and your preparation would be great.
是的，先生现在我只做复习和答题练习
Yes, sir. Now I just do revision and answer writing practice.
但要不断加强准备工作
But keep boosting your preparation.
继续参加测试
Keep participating in the Combat test
还有安库尔，不要冒险
and Ankur, don't take chances.
先生，像你这样的老师是不会让我们冒险的
Sir, teachers like you don't let us take chances.
学生们过了很久才明白这件事
Students understand this thing very late.
先生，您的晚课今天就开始了
Sir, your evening batch has started today.
是的，这是他们今天的第一节课
Yes. It was their first class today.
这意味着今天你可能已经明白了 Manohar Prakash 的笑话
That means today you would have cracked the joke of Manohar Prakash.
头等舱应该是这样的，不是吗？
First-class should be like this, isn't it?
我们喝茶吧
Let's have tea.
干得好
Good job.
你怎么没接我的电话？
Why didn't you receive my call?
有个问题，兄弟
There is a problem, buddy.
我能做什么? 我是个失败者，为什么你要把问题告诉一个失败者？
What can I do? I am a failure. Why are you telling this to a failure?
- 跟别人说去吧-阿比拉什打过电话了
- Tell it to someone else. - Abhilash had called.
- 真的?-是的
- Really? - Yes.
他说了什么? 他道歉了吗？
What did he say? Did he apologize?
他没有直接道歉
He did not apologize directly.
他至少应该道歉
He should have apologized at least.
- 这不是问题-那问题是什么
- This is not the problem. - Then what is the problem.
问题是他会参加婚礼
The problem is that he is coming for the wedding.
这就是..
That's what...
我告诉过你他会来参加婚礼的，我不是说过吗？
I had told you that he would come for the wedding. Didn't I say that?
这有什么问题? 是你想让他来参加婚礼的
What is the problem with this? You wanted him to come for the wedding.
- 我什么时候想要的?-我是说..
- When did I want that? - I mean...
但如果他来了，那么不管是什么..
but if he comes then whatever it is...
但是什么？
But what?
如果他来参加婚礼
If he comes for the wedding
然后你们两个之间的问题就可以解决了
then the problem between the two of you can be sorted out.
你不明白
You are not understanding.
怎么了，兄弟？
What happened, buddy?
达莉娅也会出席婚礼
Dhairya would also be there at the wedding.
达莉娅怎么会在那里? 我没有把她加入 WhatsApp 群组
How would Dhairya be there? I did not add her to the WhatsApp group.
达莉娅不在群里
Dhairya is not in the group.
达莉娅在哪里？
Where is Dhairya?
她不在那儿，我没有邀请她
She is not there. I did not invite her.
发生什么事了，兄弟？
What has happened, buddy?
我要娶的人就是达莉娅
I am getting married to Dhairya.
什么？
What?
我要娶的人就是达莉娅
I am getting married to Dhairya.